<resources>
    <string name="app_name">SPC App</string>
    <string name="navigation_drawer_open">Open navigation drawer</string>
    <string name="navigation_drawer_close">Close navigation drawer</string>
    <string name="nav_header_title">San Pablo City Application</string>
    <string name="nav_header_subtitle">android.studio@android.com</string>
    <string name="nav_header_desc">Navigation header</string>
    <string name="action_bpo">BPLO Fill Up</string>
    
    <string name="history1">

        \t \t The earliest historical record of the City of San Pablo dates
        back to pre-Spanish times when four (4) big barrios bounded by Mt. Banahaw
        and Mt. Makiling composed Sampaloc. \n \n

        \t \t In 1521, Sampaloc was changed to San Pablo De Los Montes, which became
        a parish in 1556 and then a municipality in 1647.  In 1899, a Municipal
        Government was established with Inocente Martinez as Municipal President
        in 1902 when the Civil Government was granted independence from the Province
        of Laguna.  On May 7, 1940, the charter bill sponsored by Congressman Tomas
        Dizon was approved.  The bill became known as the City Charter of San Pablo
        or Commonwealth Act No. 520. The City was inaugurated on March 30, 1941 with Dr.
        Potenciano Malvar as the appointed City Mayor. \n \n

        \t \t Over the years, it has flourished as a 1st class City.
        It is now being governed by Hon. Loreto S. Amante as a
        first term City Mayor until June 30, 2016. \n

    </string>

    <string name="Location1">

       \t \t San Pablo City also known as the City of Seven Lakes is located
        at geographical coordinates 14 4’ north latitude and 121east latitude.
        It is about 87 south-southwest of the City of Manila with Rizal Park as reference point.
        The City is the center of other progressive cities in Southern Luzon as it belongs to a vital economic hub.
        The City at 14 15’ 20” north latitude is bounded by the mountain ranges of Kaisungan and
        Calauan Hills in the south; Mabilog in the northwest; San Cristobal and Banahaw
        Mountains in the east; and Susong-Dalaga, Napayong and Masalukot Hills in the south to the southeast. \n

    </string>

    <string name="home">

        \t \t San Pablo City also known as the City of Seven Lakes is located
        at geographical coordinates 14 4’ north latitude and 121east latitude.
        It is about 87 south-southwest of the City of Manila with Rizal Park as reference point.
        The City is the center of other progressive cities in Southern Luzon as it belongs to a vital economic hub.
        The City at 14 15’ 20” north latitude is bounded by the mountain ranges of Kaisungan and
        Calauan Hills in the south; Mabilog in the northwest; San Cristobal and Banahaw
        Mountains in the east; and Susong-Dalaga, Napayong and Masalukot Hills in the south to the southeast. \n

    </string>
    <string name="Climate">

        \t \t In San Pablo City, the months from January to April constitute the dry season and the remaining months
        as wet season.  The relatively dry season makes the pattern closest to Type III in the Corona classification.
        Warm temperature and high humidity is experienced in the city throughout the year with small seasonal variation.\n \n
       \t \t  And because of its tropical climate precipitation within the city occurs only as rain.
        It is affected however, by the Southwest Monsoon and cyclonic storms which subject it to wet climate. \n

    </string>

    <string name="TotalLand1">

       \t \t  The City of San Pablo has a total land area of 19,899 hectares,
        77.16% of which is devoted to crop production. \n

    </string>


    <string name="Population1">

      \t \t The city’s population in 1989 was 186,810, showing an average annual rate of increase of 2.46 percent since 1980.
        One half of this population was from ages 1 to 19 years. The poblacion population was 30 percent of the total,
        females slightly outnumbering the males. The labor force ranges from 15-20 years of age. \n \n

        \t \t San Pablo City is the fifth most populous local government unit in the province of Laguna.
        In 2007 it has a population of 237,259 or 9.69 percent of the total provincial population.
        Based on the 2010 census of population and housing as of May 1, 2010, the city’s population is 248,890. \n


    </string>

<string name="listofevents">
         -   Coconut Festival
    \n  -	City Fiesta
    \n  -	Holy Week Celebration
    \n  -	Flores de Mayo/Santacruzan
    \n  -	San Pablo City Foundation Day
    \n  -	Festival of Seven Lakes
    \n  -	Laguna Day
    \n  -	Rambutan/Lanzones Festival
    \n  -	Festival of Lights

</string>

    <string name="listofevents2">

         January 9-14
      	\n January 15
        \n March/April
        \n  May 1-31
        \n May 7
        \n May 31
        \n June 19
        \n October
        \n December

    </string>

    <string name="history3">
      \t \t  In ancient times, San Pablo was known as the village of Sampalok.
        It was an upland realm surrounded by mountain ranges and quiescent volcanic peaks.
        Belief was that mountain making movements or orogeny  had thrust lower lying areas
        to uplands and low rolling plains after extensive volcanisms took place millions of
        years ago and  where caesal piniaceus tamarind  or sampalok trees grew  in wild
        abundance. This upland realm became our hometown, San Pablo de los Montes. \n
    </string>

    <string name="Sampalok">
        \t \t Sampalok was a large and prospering village which had its own system of government
        and culture. Barangays already existed and each was headed by a chieftain who
        was also known as  Gatpuno. Foremost among them were Gat Paguil, Gat Sungayan,
        Gat Salakab and Gat Pulintan.  Cultural development was manifested in marriage
        patterns, religion and social groups. \n \n
        \t \t Even crude written symbols of communications
        were used to record simple trades and forms of literature although oral handing of
        customs, beliefs, songs and practices was preferred. The natives had a glimpse of
        the outside world thru Chinese traders who were the first group to be in contact
        with as evidenced by  ceramic pieces  that were unearthed and carbon-dated. \n
    </string>

    <string name="Spaniards">
     \t \t   In search of gold the first Spanish troops under Captain Juan de Salcedo reached
        the upland realm of Sampalok in 1571 and immediately announced governance in
        the name of the king of Spain. Administration of its affairs was turned over to
        the   Augustinian missionaries who succeeded in converting most of the natives
        to Christianity. \n \n
        \t \t Fiesta was introduced as part of religious rituals.  Consequently,
        some barangay villages were renamed after saints as a reason for the festivity.
        Native chieftains were renamed cabesa de barangay and in 1647 Sampalok was renamed
        San Pablo de los Montes in honor of St. Paul the First Hermit and became an independent
        municipality with a gobernadorcillo or capitan as its head. \n \n

        \t \t  Centuries of Spanish colonization of the Philippine Islands had left its indelible
        imprint on the social, economic and political life of the country. In San Pablo de
        los Montes the gridiron plan for its central village or cabecera had been replicated
        from   communities that were founded  under the Spanish empire which conspicuously
        featured  a central plaza. From 1648 to 1898  249 gobernadorcillos  and 94 parish priests
        had been  installed  in San Pablo de los Montes. \n \n

        \t \t   Over the years there was genial and friendly relationship between the natives
        and the religious who wielded the civil authority. Until the flames of revolution against
        Spain that  was ignited by the execution of Dr. Jose P. Rizal who was well known to the
        local citizenry had crept into San Pablo de los Montes and  produced revolutionists
        and local  heroes. \n \n

        \t \t   In the face of impending defeat the Spanish troops left the town
        and the Philippine Flag was raised in the town plaza on June 6, 1898.
        The revolutionists led by General Juan Cailles immediately appointed prominent
        citizens as councilmen and town officials to effect local administration. \n

    </string>

    <string name="american">
      \t \t The subsequent defeat of the Spanish colonizers set the stage for another war – the
        Filipino-American war and the inevitable American occupation and establishment of
        the Philippine Commonwealth. Although Manila was captured by the American troops on
        June 30, 1898 the first American cavalry arrived in San Pablo on January 14, 1900
        after taking Santa Cruz and Calamba earlier and routed the  local freedom fighters. \n \n

        \t \t America’s pacification drive and grant of amnesty to freedom-fighters did much to
        quell animosity and distrust among the local citizenry and on January 24, 1901 U.S.
        military authorities appointed Don Pedro de Gorostiza as municipal president of San
        Pablo.\n \n

     \t \t Civil government in the Philippines was inaugurated on July 4, 1901.
        It was ushered in locally by the elite of San Pablo  which was composed of the
        influential, wealthy and closely related families  who easily dominated the fledgling
        electoral process. \n \n

      \t \t Don Marcos Paulino was the first elective municipal president of San Pablo (1902-1904).
        The other municipal presidents who succeeded him are as follows: \n \n

        1905-1907   -   Don Melecio Fule \n
        1908-1910   -   Don Cornelio Alcantara \n
        1911-1913   -   Don Simeon Gesmundo \n
        1914-1916   -   Don Marcial Alimario \n
        1916-1918   -   Don Feliciano Exconde \n
        1919-1921   -   Don Potenciano Cabrera \n
        1922-1924   -   Don Isidoro Alvaran \n
        1925-1927   -   Don Zacarias Sahagun \n
        1928-1931   -   Don Crispin Calabia \n
        1931-1934   -   Don Gaudencio Aquino \n
        1935-1938   -   Don Inocencio Barleta \n
        1938-1940   -   Don Cristeto Brion \n \n

       \t \t On May 7, 1940, San Pablo became a city thru enactment and approval of Commonwealth Act No.
        520 which was sponsored by Assemblyman Tomas Dizon. Dr. Potenciano Malvar became the first
        appointive City Mayor. \n

    </string>

    <string name="japanese">

        \t \t In the morning of December 25, 1941 Japanese fighter planes dropped bombs in the city
        and strafed people and edifices. They left behind a harrowing scene of ruins and death.
        On December 30, 1941 General Susuma  Morioka arrived and took over San Pablo in the name
        of the invading Japanese Imperial Forces. \n \n

       \t \t World War II brought extensive damage to the city in terms of lives lost and property
        destroyed. It brought out the worst and the best in men – from the dreaded notoriety
        of the local kempetai and makapili collaborators  to the admirable heroism of the local
        guerillas and freedom fighters one of whom was Cipriano B. Colago who became the first elected
        City Mayor of San Pablo. Japanese occupation ended when the American troops marched into
        the city on April 4, 1945. \n

    </string>

   <string name="marcos">
      \t \t On September 21, 1972 President Ferdinand E. Marcos issued Proclamation No. 1081 which placed
       the entire Philippine archipelago under Martial Law.  Among others, it paved the way for the
       issuance of Presidential Decree No. 86 dated December 31, 1972; Presidential Decree No. 86-A
       dated January 5, 1973 and Presidential Decree No. 86-B dated January 7, 1973.  All these decrees
       were contributory to the creation of Citizen Assemblies or Barangays. Under  these decrees 80
       barangays were created in the city. \n \n

       \t \t  On February 25, 1986 the so-called EDSA Revolution or People Power Revolution broke
       out following withdrawal of support by Defense Minister Enrile and Philippine Constabulary
       Chief Fidel V. Ramos to the martial law government. President Marcos fled the country and went
       to Hawaii were he died on September 28,1989.  \n \n

       \t \t  A Revolutionary Government was established by President Corazon C. Aquino who was catapulted to
       power by the EDSA revolution and local government executives all over the country were either
       booted out of office or retained.  In San Pablo City, Mayor Cesar P. Dizon was replaced by
       long-time political rival, former City Mayor Zacarias A. Ticzon as OIC Mayor. \n \n

       \t \t  Upon filing of his certificate of candidacy Ticzon was replaced by OIC Jose de Roma who was later on replaced
       by OIC Ruben Adarlo of the MILG.  Upon ratification of the Philippine Constitution of 1986
       normalcy in governance returned and so did the electoral process. \n

   </string>

    <string name="history2">
      \t \t  In ancient times, San Pablo was known as the village of Sampalok. It was an upland
        realm surrounded by mountain ranges and quiescent volcanic peaks. Belief was that
        mountain making movements or orogeny  had thrust lower lying areas to uplands and low
        rolling plains after extensive volcanisms took place millions of years ago and
        where caesal piniaceus tamarind  or sampalok trees grew  in wild abundance. This
        upland realm became our hometown, San Pablo de los Montes. \n

    </string>

    <string name="sanpablos">

       \t \t San Pablo City is host to diverse culture, customs and traditions. This is attributed
        to the city’s location, being inland, that makes it accessible from neighboring towns,
        cities and provinces. Settlers from Batangas, Quezon and the Bicolandia, to mention a
        few, have been integrated in the mainstream of city life. They were the products of
        inter-marriage, business or related interest, professional calling or occupational
        pursuits, simple transfer of residence and others. \n \n

        \t \t Tagalog is the most widely used dialect in the city. However, other dialects like Bikol,
        Kapampangan, Cebuano, Waray, Ilocano and Maguindanao  are also spoken by migrants. \n \n

        \t \t As Filipino and English are both the official languages of the Philippines they are
        spoken in the city with the latter being used as a medium of instructions in the
        academe and in most government communications. Outside of the two mentioned languages,
        Chinese and Sanskrit are also noticeably used. \n \n

        \t \t Roman Catholic is the biggest religious denomination in San Pablo City. This is
        followed by Iglesia ni Kristo, Aglipayans, Evangelical and other minor denominations. \n


    </string>

    <string name="postwarmayor">
        \t \t Alfonso Farcon - 1945-1946 \n
        \t \t Tomas Dizon - 1946 \n
        \t \t Fernando Bautista - 1947-1949 \n
        \t \t Marciano Brion - 1950-1951 \n
        \t \t Artemio Fule - 1951-1953 \n
        \t \t Tomas Dizon - 1953-1955 \n

    </string>
    <string name="education">

       \t \t In San Pablo City, there are sixty three (63) public elementary schools offering
        elementary and pre – elementary education which are distributed in the seven (7)
        districts of the city; seventy six (76) day care centers, fifty one (51) private
        pre-elemetary schools, twenty seven (27) private elementary schools, fourteen (14)
        public secondary schools, fifteen (15) private secondary schools, six (6) tertiary
        school and ten (10) vocational school, offering short term courses. \n \n

        \t \t Paaralang Pag-ibig at Pag-asa, established since 1970’s as permanent special
        education center with the aim of providing the needs of differently able and
        special children with autism, hearing impairment, visual impairment, intellectual
        disabilities and multiple handicaps. It helps the handicapped to be functionally
        literate and economically productive. \n \n

        \t \t As per record of the Department of Education, the average teacher-student ratio in
        public elementary schools for school year 2008-2009 is 1.33 and average classroom-pupil
        ratio is 1.35 which conforms with the DECS standard which is 1:40. \n

    </string>

    <string name="population">
        \t \t San Pablo City is the fifth most populous local government unit in the Province of Laguna.
        In 2007 it has a population of 237,259 or 9.69% of the total provincial population.
        As reckoned in the same year, the Annual Growth Rate of the city’s population is 1.84%.
        Based on this the city’s projected population for 2010 is 250,575.  \n \n



    </string>

    <string name="livelihood">

   \t \t The City of San Pablo is self sufficient in terms of fish, poultry eggs, corn, assorted
        vegetables, pineapple and root crops. However, it is not so when it comes to basic food
        commodities such as rice, livestock and poultry meat products. Low production of these
        commodities is attributed to limited areas for rice. Some quarters believe though that
        strict guidelines of the city for the operation and establishment of swine farms also is
        one of the reasons for non-expansion of the business. Few poultry raisers are re-investing
        for the construction of broiler poultry buildings. \n


    </string>

    <string name="homes">\t \t The earliest historical record of the City of San
        Pablo dates back to pre-Spanish times when four (4) big barrios bounded
        by Mt. Banahaw and Mt. Makiling composed Sampaloc. \n
        \n
        \t \t In 1521, Sampaloc was changed to San Pablo De Los Montes,
        which became a parish in 1556 and then a municipality in 1647.
        In 1899, a Municipal Government was established with Inocente
        Martinez as Municipal President in 1902 when the Civil Government
        was granted independence from the Province of Laguna.  On May 7, 1940,
        the charter bill sponsored by Congressman Tomas Dizon was approved.
        The bill became known as the City Charter of San Pablo or Commonwealth
        Act No. 520.  The City was inaugurated on March 30, 1941 with Dr. Potenciano Malvar
        as the appointed City Mayor. \n
    </string>
    <string name="Reps"> Republic of the Philippines \n

    </string>
    <string name="Rep">
        All content in the public \n
        domain unless otherwise stated
    </string>

<string name="home2">
        \t \t In 1521, Sampaloc was changed to San Pablo De Los Montes,
        which became a parish in 1556 and then a municipality in 1647.
        In 1899, a Municipal Government was established with Inocente
        Martinez as Municipal President in 1902 when the Civil Government
        was granted independence from the Province of Laguna.  On May 7, 1940,
        the charter bill sponsored by Congressman Tomas Dizon was approved.
        The bill became known as the City Charter of San Pablo or Commonwealth
        Act No. 520.  The City was inaugurated on March 30, 1941 with Dr. Potenciano Malvar
        as the appointed City Mayor. \n
    </string>
    <string name="Mission"> \t \t To implement the City development programs through sustainable and efficient delivery of
        public services in partnership with the private sector \n</string>
    <string name="Vision"> \t \t San Pablo, the City of Seven Lakes a premier
        agricultural and light industrial zone, education hub and tourist destination in CALABARZON \n</string>

<string name="city_info_frontline">	ISSUANCE OF OATH OF OFFICE AND APPOINTMENT OF ELECTIVE / APPOINTIVE BARANGAY OFFICIALS AND BARANGAY   TANODS.

</string>

    <string name="city_info_frontline_four"> MAKES ANNOUNCEMENT OF THE FOLLOWING: \n
        -	BARANGAY AND CITY GOVERNMENT PROGRAMS/ACTIVITIES \n
        -	VEHICULAR ACCIDENT \n
        -	ASSISTANCE (MERALCO, WATER DISTRICT, AMBULANCE, FIRE INCIDENT) \n
        -	MISSING ANIMAL / PERSON \n
        -	CARNAPED / ABANDONED VEHICLE \n
        -	ROBBERY / HOLD-UP \n
        -	PSAF / POLICE ASSISTANCE \n


    </string>
    
    <string name="education_shoolphilosophy">
        \t\t The school is deeply committed towards the integral formation
        of the human person, with a profound faith in God, in his fellow men and himself by providing its
        students the full development of their physical, intellectual, social and cultural endowment for
        effective participation in various professions and industrial occupations and to enable them to
        enjoy reasonable quality of life to be able to contribute to the upliftment of the human society. \n </string>

    <string name="education_visionstatement">
        \t\t Dalubhasaan ng Lunsod ng San Pablo shall emerge
        as one of the best locally funded universities in the country and a center of excellence
        in Education. The College foresees its graduates with strong moral fiber, proud of his race
        and prepared for exemplary global participation in the arts, sciences, humanities, education
        and business, enjoying a quality of life and abundance;  graduates who are living in peace
        and in harmony with nature and their fellowmen and above all, God-fearing. \n </string>

    <string name="education_missionstatement">
        \t\t The mission of DLSP is to provide for the total development
        of all the members of the academic community particularly its students through balanced and relevant
        program of activities in its curricular and co-curricular offerings fortified by strong Filipino values and ideals. \n  \n

        \t\t Through its educational program, the college seeks to develop academic excellence,
        professional competence, social awareness, social upliftment and appreciation of Philippine heritage. \n \n

        \t\t  More specifically, DLSP’s establishment is to render educational services to the poor residents of the community. \n
    </string>

    <string name="population_population">
       \t \t San Pablo City is the fifth most populous local government unit in the Province of Laguna.
        In 2007 it has a population of 237,259 or 9.69% of the total provincial population.
        As reckoned in the same year, the Annual Growth Rate of the city’s population is 1.84%.
        Based on this the city’s projected population for 2010 is 250,575. \n \n


        \t \t  Historically, the Annual Growth Rate during the period 1960-1970 posted  an all time high
        of 4.08%. This was influenced by the influx of migrant workers together with their families
        as the motor works ( jeepney body-building) industries and agri-based oil refineries boomed. \n \n

        \t \t  In 1975-1995 the AGR teetered (2.01%, 2.45%, 2.07% and 2.43%) as labor demand from Calamba
        and Sta Rosa, which are now cities, and the Municipality of San Pedro sharply increased due
        to construction and  subsequent operation of a number of industrial parks or manufacturing
        companies in those areas. Out-migration then was inevitable. \n \n

        \t \t  The AGR continued to drop during the period 2000-2007 to 1.84% World-wide recession was looming
        and the pursuit for gainful employment became naturally acute. Diaspora ensued and soon enough
        a sizable number of city residents moved to foreign lands in search of greener pastures. Another
        aspect worth considering is the change in the lifestyle and outlook of the people. Young
        professionals or couples are more inclined to raise a smaller family usually with one or two kids.
        Still others prefer to find mates on live-in and childless basis for a certain period of time. \n

    </string>

    <string name="population_censusdata">
        1903 \n
        1918 \n
        1939 \n
        1948 \n
        1960 \n
        1970 \n
        1975 \n
        1980 \n
        1990 \n
        1995 \n
        2000 \n
        2007
    </string>

    <string name="population_tp_laguna">
        148,606 \n
        195,546 \n
        279,505 \n
        321,247 \n
        472,064 \n
        699,736 \n
        803,750 \n
        973,104 \n
        1,370,232 \n
        1,631,082 \n
        1,965,872 \n
        2,473,530
    </string>

    <string name="population_tp_spc">
        22,612 \n
        31,399 \n
        46,311 \n
        50,435 \n
        70,680 \n
        105,517 \n
        116,607 \n
        131,655 \n
        161,630 \n
        183,757 \n
        207,927 \n
        237,262
    </string>

    <string name="population_agr_laguna">
        - \n
        - \n
        - \n
        - \n
        - \n
        - \n
        - \n
        - \n
        3.32 \n
        4.08 \n
        4.08 \n
        3.22
    </string>
    <string name="population_agr_spc">
        - \n
        2.21% \n
        1.86% \n
        .95% \n
        .17% \n
        4.08% \n
        2.01% \n
        2.45% \n
        2.07% \n
        2.43% \n
        2.68% \n
        1.84%
    </string>

    <string name="population_migration">
       \t \t Five years ago, out of 215,288  household population (five years old and over )
        94.24 percent never leave nor transfer their residence to other place. On the
        hand, 0.43 percent of the household population moved from other municipalities
        of Laguna , 2.58 percent moved from other province and 0.25 percent migrated
        from foreign country. \n \n
       \t \t In the three migratory movements, there were more females than males, larger
        by about 2.17 percent in the inter-municipality migration within the province,
        by 1.99 percent among migrants from other provinces and 2.05 percent among former
        residents of foreign lands. \n

    </string>

    <string name="population_density">
        \t \t San  Pablo City has a total land area of 21,400 hectares. Is is estimated that
        the gross density of the city was 8.78 persons per hectare in 2009. By area
        classification, the gross urban density is 29.28 persons per hectare while
        there are 11 persons in rural areas per hectare. It is expected that by year
        2010 the population density of the city will be 12 persons per hectare. \n \n

       \t \t Among the urban barangays, Brgy. II-A has the highest density with 666 persons per
        hectare while the least density is in Brgy. Atisan and  Brgy. San Cristobal, Brgy.
        San Jose as these barangays have a larger land areas. \n \n

       \t \t While it is heavily congested in the urban areas, rural barangays of the city have
        vast land areas to settle its inhabitants in  Brgy. San Cristobal the biggest barangay in
        terms of land area has the least population density of 2.00 per hectare as it is a
        mountainous area. \n
    </string>

    <string name="population_household">

       \t \t San Pablo City has 80 barangays-39 urban and 41 rural barangays. San Pablo although
        classified as chartered city is predominantly rural. Based on the year 2007 census,
        more than one-half (52.90%) of its population reside in the rural areas while 47.10
        percent are in the urban areas. \n \n

        \t \t Further, in 2009, the number of household population is 243,759 of which 46,715 reside
        in the urban areas while 197,044 are in the rural areas, with an average household size
        of 4.7, total number of household is 52,352. Of the total household population, Barangay
        Del Remedio has the biggest number of populace with a total of 13,975 with 4.7 members
        for every household. This can be attributed to numerous subdivisions developed in barangay
        Del Remedio as a result of in-immigration and natural increase. The smallest number of
        household population is in Brgy. VII-D with 19 households. \n
    </string>

    <string name="population_age">
        \t \t San Pablo City has a young age structure. Thirty four percent
        (34%) of the population is below age fifteen (15) years old.
        Just over sixty four percent (64%) of the population is in the
        economically productive age (15-64) and those over sixty five
        (65) years of age constitute 4.04%. This young age structure
        has two  (2) primary effects: \n \n

       \t \t(1)	A young age structure regardless of the total fertility
        rate or the average number of children born to a woman in her
        life time, presupposes that the population will continue to grow for
        a long time. This is because of the large number of women currently
        in their reproductive ages. This phenomenon is called population momentum. \n \n

        \t \t(2) The dependency ratio, the number of dependents (young
        people aged 0-14 and old people aged 65 and over) are being
        supported by the economically  productive age group ( 15-64 years old). \n \n


        \t \t In San Pablo City, the age dependency ratio is 61.3/100persons which is
        considered high. A high dependency ratio means greater consumption and
        less saving. A youth population (0-14 years old) needs food, health care
        and education. Meeting this demand places a  strain in the city government’s
        ability to provide resources for their dependent population. \n \n

        \t \t The sex ratio is 98:1 meaning there are 98 males for every 100 females.
        By age group, it is observed that under 14 years old there are more boys
        than girls while ages 15 years old and over there are more women, particularly
        in the productive age, than that of their male counterpart, implying that
        if family planning will not be fully implemented it will aggravate the
        population growth, therefore, sustain the current social and economic conjuncture. \n
    </string>

    <string name="education_grade">
       \t \t Residents of San Pablo with ages 5 years old and over who have completed elementary
        education showed marked preponderance with 39.71% (96,796). Of the the total household
        population 3.17% (7,727) finished pre-school; 29.75% (72,567) reached  secondary school;
        3.39 (8,264) attended vocational school; 18.89 (45,778) enrolled in college. \n \n

        \t \t In the high school or secondary level only 46.39% (33,663) graduated while 53.61%
        (38,879) finished vocational course. \n \n

        \t \t There are 59.05% (27,033) became academic degree holders 40.95% (18,745) 18,745 became
        undergraduates and 293 finished post baccalaureate. \n \n

        \t \t Those who have no grade completed comprise 4.25% (10,360) and there are about 0.81 (1,9974)
        who did not disclose their educational attainment. \n

    </string>



    <string name="agricultural_corps">
       \t \t  There are several crops grown in San Pablo City (SPC). These are classified into
        seasonal crops and permanent crops. Seasonal crops are dominated by assorted lowland
        vegetable including legumes. Other seasonal crops grown are irrigated rice, pineapple,
        corn and root crops. Permanent crops are dominated by coconut followed by fruit
        bearing trees like lanzones, rambutan and citrus. Banana is also grown as permanent crop. \n
    </string>

    <string name="agricultural_corplands">
       \t \t The total area planted to crops by the end of 2009 was estimated at a little
        more than 20,000.00 hectares. (Table 28). Although established as a city, San
        Pablo has vast rural areas for agricultural production such as crops and livestock.
        Coconut area is estimated to be ¾ of the total hectarage followed by fruit bearing
        trees then lowland vegetables. \n
    </string>
    <string name="crop">
        1. Seasonal Crop \n
        \t a. Irrigated rice \n
        \t b. Non-irrigated rice \n
        \t c. Pineapple \n
        \t d. Corn \n
        \t e. Lowland vegetables, Legumes \n
        \t f. Rootcrops \n
        \t 2.  Permanent Crops \n
        \t a.  Coconut \n
        \t b.  Lanzones \n
        \t c.  Rambutan \n
        \t d.  Citrus \n
        \t e.  Banana
    </string>
    <string name="area_planted">
        - \n
        554.83 \n
        - \n
        293.95 \n
        191.00 \n
        1,008.67 \n
        45.50 \n
        - \n
        15,154.00 \n
        1,916.06 \n
        433.08 \n
        133.06 \n
        332.47
    </string>

    <string name="total_area">
        2,093.95 \n
        - \n
        -\n
        -\n
        -\n
        -\n
        -\n
        17,968.67\n
        -\n
        -\n
        -\n
        -\n
        -\n
    </string>

    <string name="percent_crop">
        10.44 \n
        (2.77)\n
        -\n
        -\n
        -\n
        -\n
        -\n
        89.56\n
        (75.53)\n
        -\n
        -\n
        -\n
        -\n
    </string>


    <string name="crop_production">
       \t \t The total volume of production of all crops in SPC is estimated at close to 74,000 m.t.
        (Table 29). Of this total yield, coconut accounted for more than one-half of the produce
        followed by vegetables of all types. Rice and pineapple follows, both with a 5% contribution
        to the total crop production in 2009. \n
    </string>

    <string name="crop2">
        1.  Rice, all types \n
        2.  Coconut \n
        3.  Banana \n
        4.  Fruit Trees, all types \n
        5.  Vegetables, all types (Legumes) \n
        6.  Root crops \n
        7.  Pineapple \n
        8.  Corn
    </string>
    <string name="production">
        4,946.51\n
        49,098.96\n
        1,547.40\n
        1,013.69\n
        11,045.02\n
        682.50\n
        3,858.08\n
        1,146.00
    </string>
    <string name="percent_crop2">
        6.75\n
        66.95\n
        2.11\n
        1.38\n
        15.06\n
        0.93\n
        5.26\n
        1.56
    </string>
    <string name="carabao">
        \t \t Carabao in San Pablo City is very important for draft purposes. Carabao population in 2005 to
        2009 was observed to slightly decline from 1,731 to just around 1,300. This can be attributed
        to the decrease in rice irrigated areas a little less than 100 hectares. Some farmers also sell
        the animals for financial needs and lack of area where the animal is tethered.
        Although not shown in data, breeds of carabao are being upgraded to dairy types for future
        development of the animal for milk purposes. The population appeared to be highest in Barangay
        Sta. Maria and Santissimo Rosario. \n
    </string>
    <string name="cattle">
       \t \t Cattle population in the rural areas of the city is observed to be steady from 2005 to
        2009 with a population of around 4,000 heads. Cattle are popularly being raised for
        meat purposes. The animal is observed to be highest in Barangay Sta. Maria and Soledad. \n
    </string>
    <string name="pigs">
       \t \t The swine population is observed to be steady from 2005 to 2009 with a population of around
        5,000 heads and 25,000 heads for backyard and commercial raisers respectively. The backyard
        swine population is observed to be highest in San Crispin followed by Sta. Felomina then
        San Miguel. \n
    </string>
    <string name="goat">
       \t \t There is a great increase in goat population from 2005 to 2009. The number doubled from 990
        to 2,564 heads. These are attributed to the introduction of imported breeds by private growers.
        There is also an increase in the number of individuals who ventured into goat farming due to
        its popularity in other areas and upgrading activities. \n
    </string>
    <string name="horse">
        \t \t The horse population is also steady for the year  2005 to 2009. The animal is observed to be
        highest in number in Barangays Sta. Isabel and San Jose. \n
    </string>
    <string name="poultry">
       \t \t Backyard population decreased from 2005 to 2007 (38,583-> 36,475)
        and then increased from 2007 to 2009 (36,475->38,378). There is a
        steady increase in population in commercial farms from around 2,000,000
        to 2,500,000. Backyard broiler operation is
        observed to be highest in Barangays San Lorenzo and Sto. Angel. \n
    </string>
    <string name="ducks">
        \t \t Duck population remained to be steady with a number
        of around 11,500. It is observed
        to be highest in Barangays San Isidro and Santissimo Rosario. \n </string>
    <string name="fisheries">
        \t \t San Pablo City is also known as “City of Seven Lakes”. The names of the lakes are Sampaloc,
        Pandin, Yambo, Mohicap, Palakpakin, Calibato and Bunot Lakes. The lakes have for many generations
        provided food and livelihood, leisure and respite for the citizens of the city. \n \n

        \t \t  The fishery sector is very significant economic resource in San Pablo City due to
        the presence of these lakes where large quantities of fish are being harvested. It
        is estimated that a total of 4,437.92 metric tons is being harvested in all the lakes
        of San Pablo City according to CAO’s data as reported by Fisheries and Aquatic Resource
        Management Council (FARMC). The main species being produced and grown is the tilapia
        supplemented by other species.  \n \n

        \t \t  The methods of growing tilapia are mainly through fish cages being set up in all
        the lakes. The fisher folks are generally organized into a group called FARMC. \n
    </string>
    <string name="lakes">
        Sampalok Lake\n
        Bunot Lake\n
        Pandin Lake\n
        Palakpakin Lake\n
        Mohicap Lake\n
        Yambo Lake\n
        Calibato Lake\n
    </string>
    <string name="total_area_lake">
        104\n
        29.60\n
        24\n
        43\n
        14\n
        30.50\n
        43
    </string>
    <string name="area_2008">
        15.33
        6.48
        0.53
        8.56
        2.02
        0.90
        8.20

    </string>

<string name="location_geographical">
    \t \t San Pablo City is located at the southern tip of the Province of  Laguna in the
    island of Luzon at geographic coordinates, 140 4’ north latitude and 1210 19’
    east longtitude.  It is bounded by 6 municipalities and 1 city  namely Calauan,
    Laguna in the northwest;  Nagcarlan, Laguna in the northeast; Alaminos, Laguna
    in the west;  Rizal, Laguna in the east; Lipa City, Batangas in the southeastern
    tip;  and the municipalities of Tiaong and Dolores, Quezon  in the south.
    All adjoining municipalities and city have entry points making San Pablo
    accessible from virtually all directions. \n \n

    \t \t Kilometerage distance from the National Capital Region is about 82 kilometers
    and located southwesterly of Manila. \n
</string>

    <string name="location_municipality">
        Calauan, Laguna \n
        Alaminos, Laguna \n
        Nagcarlan, Laguna \n
        Rizal, Laguna \n
        Dolores, Quezon \n
        Tiaong, Quezon \n
        Lipa City, Batangas

    </string>
    <string name="location_distance">
        9.5 \n
        10.00 \n
        14.00 \n
        9.00 \n
        11.00 \n
        14.00 \n
        36
    </string>
    <string name="location_topography">
        \t\t Topography is generally plain  to gently sloping with small portions
        of rolling  to very steep hills on the northern, eastern and southern
        edges.  It is bounded by the mountain ranges of Kalusungan and Calauan
        Hills in the north;  Mabilog on the northeast; San Cristobal and Banahaw
        Mountains in the east; and Susong Dalaga, Napayong and Masalukot Hills
        in the south to southeast. \n
    </string>
    <string name="location_climate">
       \t \t In San Pablo City, the months from January to April constitute the dry
        season and the remaining months as wet season.  The relatively dry season
        makes the pattern closest to Type III in the Corona classification.
        Warm temperature and high humidity is experienced in the city throughout
        the year with small seasonal variation.  And because of its tropical
        climate precipitation within the city occurs only as rain.  It is affected
        however, by the Southwest Monsoon and cyclonic storms which subject
        it to wet climate.\n
    </string>

    <string name="tab_govphil">The Integrated Government Philippines (iGovPhil) is a joint program \n of the
        Department of Information and Communications Technology \n (DICT) and the
        Advanced Science and Technology Institute of the \n Department of Science and Technology (DOST-ASTI)\n
    </string>
    <string name="form">I DECLARE UNDER PENALTY OF PERJURY that the
        forgoing information are true based on my personal knowledge and authentic records.
        Further, I agree to comply with the regulatory requirements and other deficiencies within thirty
        (30) days from release of the business permit.
    </string>
    <string name="gallery_">San Pablo, officially the City of San Pablo, (Tagalog: Lungsod ng San Pablo), or simply
        known as San Pablo City, is a 1st class city in the province of Laguna, Philippines. According to the 2015
        census, it has a population of 266,068 peopl
    </string>

    <string name="point_service">
        1.When we go to work, we will come in complete uniform and display our identification cards. \n\n

        2.We will greet our clients with a sincere smile. \n\n

        3.When you enter our offce premises,we will introduce ourselves to you so that you can address usback in an apporiate manner. \n\n

        4.We will attend our clients’ inquiries within three(3)minutes. \n\n

        5.Approriate action will immediately follow your queries and you will be referred accordinly. \n\n

        6.We will make you comfortable inside our facilities while you wait for your service request. \n\n

        7.Express/special lanes are provided for Senior Citivens, pregnant women and People with Disablilites. \n\n

        8.We will teach the clients, needed requiremnts that can expedite their service request. \n\n

        9.We will promplty return your denied request and explain to you the reason forsuch, which in turn will allow us to reprocess it. \n\n

        10.Our service stations will be properly labeled that will include our organizational chart and service flow chart. \n\n

        11.Directional signs will be displayed conspicuously as guide so that you can establish familiarity with our work place. \n\n

        12.Information and complaint desk is at your service in strategic locations. \n\n

        13.An information and hotline service is available 24/7 for anyone who has queries. \n\n

        14.No noon-break policy is followed and we are to serve beyond office hours if need. \n\n

        15. A satisfied client is our happiness in the government service. \n
    </string>
    <string name="performance_pledge1">
        We, the offcials and employees of the City Government of San Pablocommit to:
    </string>
    <string name="performance_pledge2">
        ssist every client and visitors with utmost courtesy and smile.\n
    </string>
    <string name="performance_pledge3">
        onitor our own ranks to ensure that services are delivered ontime \n
    </string>
    <string name="performance_pledge4">
        dequate care shall be accorded to Senior Citizens, pregnant women, children and Persons with Disabilities(PWDs) that comes our door.  \n
    </string>
    <string name="performance_pledge5">
        urture each day as a gift of opportunity to serve others.  \n
    </string>
    <string name="performance_pledge6">
        rustworthiness shall be epitome of our service delays with explanations.  \n
    </string>
    <string name="performance_pledge7">
        nsure happy clients by addressing service delays with explanations.
        To all this we pledge and commit,
        keeping in mind that we are at all times accountable
        to the people that we serve. \n
    </string>
    <string name="agency_mandate">
        \t \t All employees both rank and file and personnel holding key positions
        in different departments of the local governmaent are mandated to deliver quality service
        through the implementation of tits programs to make them effcient
        and sustainable that have been developed in partnership with the private sector. \n </string>
    <string name="strategic_directions">
        These directions can be realized by strictly following: \n\n

        1. Existing policies of the city/ agency have to be reviewed and revisited by the implementing offce.\n\n

        2. Implementation of recuitment, selection and promotion plan, along with the performance management plan,
        learningand development strategy and rewards and recognition policies have to be strictly
        observed by the city and to be upheldby the city’s implementing offcials/offcers at all times.\n\n

        3. Monitor day-to-day activities of all employees.\n\n

        4. Public service has to be the topmost priority of all employees.\n
    </string>

    <string name="back"><![CDATA[<]]></string>
    <string name="forward"><![CDATA[>]]></string>

    <!-- TODO: Remove or change this placeholder text -->
    <string name="hello_blank_fragment">Hello blank fragment</string>
    <string name="title_activity_maps">Lakbay San Pablo</string>
    <string name="title_activity_maps2">Map</string>
</resources>
